<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<quiz>
  <name>Session 04 Entry Quiz — Cryptography Prerequisites</name>
  <description>Pre-session assessment of prerequisite mathematical and computing concepts. 5 MCQ, 10 minutes, passing score 3/5.</description>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Entry Q1: Prime Numbers</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text><![CDATA[<p>What is a <strong>prime number</strong>?</p>]]></text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>A number that is divisible by itself and by 2</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. A number divisible by 2 is called an even number. The number 2 is the only prime that is even; all other primes are odd.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="100">
      <text>A number greater than 1 that is divisible only by 1 and itself</text>
      <feedback><text>Correct! Examples: 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13, 17... RSA and many other cryptographic systems rely on the difficulty of factoring large numbers that are products of two large primes.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>A number that appears only once in a sequence</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. That describes a unique element in a set, not a prime number.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>A number that cannot be expressed as a fraction</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. That describes an irrational number (like π or √2). Prime numbers are integers.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <shuffleanswers>true</shuffleanswers>
    <single>true</single>
  </question>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Entry Q2: XOR Operation</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text><![CDATA[<p>What does the <strong>XOR (exclusive OR)</strong> operation do?</p>]]></text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>Returns 1 if both bits are 1, otherwise 0</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. That describes the AND operation (1 AND 1 = 1; all others = 0).</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="100">
      <text>Returns 1 if exactly one of the two bits is 1, otherwise 0</text>
      <feedback><text>Correct! XOR: 0⊕0=0, 0⊕1=1, 1⊕0=1, 1⊕1=0. XOR is fundamental to stream ciphers and block cipher modes like CTR and CBC.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>Returns the sum of two binary numbers</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. That describes binary addition. Note that 1+1=10 in binary, but 1 XOR 1 = 0.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>Inverts all bits of a number</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. Inverting all bits is the NOT operation (bitwise complement).</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <shuffleanswers>true</shuffleanswers>
    <single>true</single>
  </question>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Entry Q3: One-Way Functions</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text><![CDATA[<p>A function is described as <strong>"one-way."</strong> What does this mean in a cryptographic context?</p>]]></text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>The function can only be applied once to any given input</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. A one-way function can be applied as many times as needed — the key property is about the difficulty of reversal, not frequency of use.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="100">
      <text>The function is easy to compute in one direction but computationally infeasible to reverse</text>
      <feedback><text>Correct! Given input x, computing f(x) is fast. Given f(x), finding x is computationally infeasible (would take millions of years). Hash functions are designed with this property.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>The function produces exactly one possible output for each input</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. That describes a deterministic function, which is a different property. One-way refers to computational irreversibility.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>The function can only run on one CPU at a time</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. One-way refers to mathematical difficulty of reversal, not hardware constraints.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <shuffleanswers>true</shuffleanswers>
    <single>true</single>
  </question>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Entry Q4: Encryption vs Encoding</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text><![CDATA[<p>What is the key difference between <strong>encryption</strong> and <strong>encoding</strong>?</p>]]></text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>Encryption is reversible; encoding is not</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. Both can be reversed. The key difference is whether a secret key is required for reversal.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>Encoding requires a key; encryption does not</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. This is backwards. Encryption requires a key; encoding does not.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="100">
      <text>Encryption requires a secret key to reverse; encoding is reversible by anyone knowing the format</text>
      <feedback><text>Correct! Base64, hex, and URL encoding can be reversed by anyone. AES encryption requires the secret key. A common mistake is treating Base64 data as "encrypted" — it provides zero security.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>They are different names for the same process</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. They are fundamentally different: encoding transforms data representation (reversible by anyone); encryption provides confidentiality (reversible only with the correct key).</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <shuffleanswers>true</shuffleanswers>
    <single>true</single>
  </question>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Entry Q5: Modulo Operation</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text><![CDATA[<p>What is the result of the <strong>modulo operation</strong>: 23 mod 7?</p>]]></text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>3</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. 23 ÷ 7 = 3 remainder 2, so 23 mod 7 = 2, not 3. The modulo gives the remainder, not the quotient.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="100">
      <text>2</text>
      <feedback><text>Correct! 23 = 3 × 7 + 2, so the remainder is 2. Modular arithmetic (a mod n) is foundational to RSA, Diffie-Hellman, and elliptic curve cryptography.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>0</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. 0 would be the result only if 23 were evenly divisible by 7, which it is not (7 × 3 = 21, not 23).</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <answer fraction="0">
      <text>7</text>
      <feedback><text>Incorrect. The modulo result is always less than the divisor (7), not equal to it.</text></feedback>
    </answer>
    <shuffleanswers>true</shuffleanswers>
    <single>true</single>
  </question>

</quiz>
