<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<quiz>
  <name>Session 09 Entry Quiz: SOC Workflow and Automation</name>
  <intro>Assess prerequisite knowledge before the session. 6 multiple-choice questions. Select the single best answer.</intro>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Q1: Alert Fatigue</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text>An analyst receives 200 security alerts during an 8-hour shift and manages to review 80 of them. The remaining 120 are ignored. What is this phenomenon called?</text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Threat overload</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="100"><text>Alert fatigue</text><feedback><text>Correct. Alert fatigue occurs when analysts are overwhelmed by volume and stop reviewing all alerts, causing real threats to be missed.</text></feedback></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Detection gap</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Signal flooding</text></answer>
    <shuffleanswers>1</shuffleanswers>
    <single>1</single>
  </question>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Q2: Alert Classification</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text>A security event was generated by an IDS rule. After investigation, the analyst confirms it is a real attack. What is the correct classification?</text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>False positive</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Benign true positive</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="100"><text>True positive</text><feedback><text>Correct. A true positive is a real security event that is correctly flagged by a detection rule.</text></feedback></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>False negative</text></answer>
    <shuffleanswers>1</shuffleanswers>
    <single>1</single>
  </question>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Q3: What is SOAR?</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text>Which of the following best describes a SOAR platform?</text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>A tool for storing and searching log files</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>A vulnerability scanner that identifies weaknesses in systems</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="100"><text>A platform that automates security workflows and integrates security tools</text><feedback><text>Correct. SOAR stands for Security Orchestration, Automation, and Response. It connects security tools and automates repetitive tasks.</text></feedback></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>An intrusion detection system based on network signatures</text></answer>
    <shuffleanswers>1</shuffleanswers>
    <single>1</single>
  </question>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Q4: MTTR Definition</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text>What does MTTR stand for in SOC operations?</text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Mean Threat Tracking Ratio</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Maximum Time to Response</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="100"><text>Mean Time to Respond (or Remediate)</text><feedback><text>Correct. MTTR measures the average time from when an incident is detected to when it is resolved.</text></feedback></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Monitored Threat Triage Record</text></answer>
    <shuffleanswers>1</shuffleanswers>
    <single>1</single>
  </question>

  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Q5: Escalation Decision</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text>A Tier 1 analyst has been investigating an alert for 25 minutes and cannot determine if it is a true positive or false positive. According to standard SOC procedure, what should they do?</text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Close the alert as a false positive to meet the SLA</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Continue investigating until they are certain</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Delete the alert from the queue and re-check tomorrow</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="100"><text>Escalate to a Tier 2 analyst</text><feedback><text>Correct. When an L1 analyst cannot resolve uncertainty within the SLA window, the correct action is to escalate — not force-close or continue indefinitely.</text></feedback></answer>
    <shuffleanswers>1</shuffleanswers>
    <single>1</single>
  </question>
  <question type="multichoice">
    <name>Q6: RACI Matrix</name>
    <questiontext format="html">
      <text>In a SOC RACI matrix, a Tier 1 analyst is listed as R (Responsible) for alert triage and I (Informed) for threat hunting. What does this mean in practice?</text>
    </questiontext>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Tier 1 must approve all threat hunting activities before they begin</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="100"><text>Tier 1 performs alert triage independently and is notified of threat hunting outcomes but does not participate</text><feedback><text>Correct. In a RACI matrix, R (Responsible) means the role performs the task; I (Informed) means they receive updates only and are not involved in execution.</text></feedback></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Tier 1 is responsible for threat hunting if no Tier 3 analyst is available</text></answer>
    <answer fraction="0"><text>Tier 1 must consult Tier 3 before closing any alert</text></answer>
    <shuffleanswers>1</shuffleanswers>
    <single>1</single>
  </question>

</quiz>
